Welcome to Business Central Launch
Edition 2026 Wave 2 release. And welcome
to this session What's New in Expense
Agent as an overview as this session is
part of Expense Agent playlist.
So, what we'll have today as an overview
because there are a lot of new things
about Expense Agent. We'll start with
improved mileage handling. Then we will
finally have enabled credit card feeds.
Then AI-driven travel expense policies
approvals process, some additional
approval improvements, travel requests,
and expense report creation per trip,
new mobile app, then on the end
compliance things about VAT and
withholding tax for employees and
expense agents.
So, let's start first with the improved
mileage handling.
But before we start,
I just want to
explain the one important thing. First,
you will see in demos during this
launch edition that we have now
refreshed web app user experience. So,
this is a little bit different. You can
see even before you start all details
what you can do there. And one thing
about availability. Now we will enable
new languages. In this moment we have
five languages enabled, but now we will
enable Czech, Dutch, Icelandic, Italian,
Norwegian, and Swedish language. But
what is more important, from October
we will enable worldwide availability.
By worldwide availability doesn't mean
that we will have everything from
October, all countries October. We'll
We'll try to do as fast as possible. It
will be gradually enablement, but it
will be really fast starting from
October. In next few months we'll enable
Expense Agent in all countries
worldwide.
So, as I said, first let's look what we
have in the improved mileage handling.
These improvements came based on your
feedback.
Uh in the early beginning we had a
really simple model how do you could set
up mileage allowance. You could choose
per mile or per kilometer and what was
allowance amount
in your currency, but now we have much
more.
First, what if you have changed
uh allowance from one year to another
year? So, now you can have
uh mileage set up per different periods.
You can define periods, this is up to
you. So, you can configure as you want.
You can
uh use only one period if you want, but
if you want you can go to multiple
periods, so system will automatically
uh start using based on your uh expense
date.
But, additional one is especially for
some countries this is even legal a
legal requirement, you need to have
different uh mileage allowance per
different vehicle type. So, now you can
have specific
uh mileage for car, for truck, for SUV,
for motorcycle. You can define what you
want to track and you can have different
mileage
uh in combination per uh vehicle type
and per date range. But again, if you
want simple one, you don't need to go in
in these complications, you do you don't
need to run mileage uh rate set up at
all. You can just set up simple model
and system will work without any
problem. We will have separate session
about mileage, so I'm inviting uh you to
go there and to look what we have.
Then, probably one of features that
if not all, but almost all uh customers
and partners waited, credit card feeds
enablement.
Um this is first release what we will
deliver and it will not be available
from October, it will be available from
December, so 2029.2.
But, what we will have there?
So, you can manually upload your credit
card statement. So, when you get credit
card statement, you can just upload and
system will process and that's it.
You will have credit card feeds as a
uh and as a entries as a record so you
can track uh original
um
imports, but what is more important for
the moment when you confirm that you
imported properly,
system will
uh automatically reconcile with your
expenses. And now we have two options
because we will uh create expense based
what is older, what is what comes first.
So, if you are reactive and you didn't
scan your receipts, system will
automatically create expenses for all
your credit card um records. And then
what you are supposed only to attach
your expenses later as a receipts and
system will process. If you do not
attach your receipts, you will not be
allowed to submit this expense. On the
other side, if you are proactive, so if
you scan your receipt in the moment when
you have this expense, system will
already have expenses, but when you um
upload
your credit card feeds, system will
automatically reconcile all these credit
card uh records with your existing uh
expenses. So, it works automatically in
a background and depends what comes
first.
More AI-driven travel expense
policy-based approvals. So, this is
completely new usage of AI, so
completely agentized process, but I will
not go so deep into details because
again we have separate session about
this topic that there we see all demos
how it works in a practice. I will only
make some overview in front of what you
need to do. So, when you start setup,
you need to enable policy compliance.
And why you need to do that? Because it
can make additional cost of using AI, so
you need to confirm you want to use
AI-driven uh policies. If you enable,
all good, everything will be
automatically there in system. So,
system will automatically check all your
uh expenses against your uh policies.
Where to set up policies?
For each of your categories, you can
find expense policies and then you can
set up multiple policies.
Uh you can see in this example, I have
for one category, airline, I have three
different policies example. So, first
one is what type of classes you can book
when you book your flight. Second one is
when you can make upgrade and third one
even for using private aircraft. So, for
all of them, this is regular uh human
readable policy, so you can copy-paste
from your existing travel expense policy
there and system will use this when you
upload your receipt. So, in my examples
here, I have
uh my
uh invoice for my flight. And in this
invoice, I do not have specified class.
So, neither economy, business, whatever.
So, it was not specified. If you see
here, system flagged automatically this
one because I'm allowed to use business
classes at specific situations. In all
other, I must use economy. But as this
is not specified, system automatically
flagged and require class,
so system can continue with approvals.
So, now
uh to explain, this is not hard
limitation. Approver can approve even if
this is flagged, even if this is not
100% compliant. This is an approver.
This is something what can help
approvers to make more reasonable
decision if uh needed to approve or not.
Okay. Uh what else we have about approv-
approvals?
We tried to improve approvals so much
because in the beginning we created a
basic approval system, but now we have
enhanced approval history and audit
trail. You will see in a separate
session about all these approvals
information what we have. But what else
now we will have interim approvers
options. We can specify approval limits,
uh alternate delegate approvals, and
even we have new approval for new brand
new functionality travel request, and we
will have separate session about travel
request, so I will not go deep here.
So, this is what is coming.
Uh it will come gradually from October
to December, but all these features will
be in next 2 months.
As I mentioned, travel request is a
brand new functionality.
And we will have separate session, but I
just want to explain what is about. So,
uh idea is if you want to travel to some
conference, you will not have you don't
want to
uh take all your receipts, for example,
for October, for November, September.
You want to have all your receipts or
expenses assigned to specific expense
report for this one trip.
So, now if you have conference, for
example, I can create travel request,
and it can go through approval process.
I can send to my manager. I can set,
okay, what I need from budget, how much
money I need, when this start and date,
uh justification, other things. But when
my manager approve this, system will
automatically create expense report for
this trip, and then then you
upload your all your receipts, system
will automatically assign all your uh
receipts specified for this trip to this
expense report. So, now we have much
more smartness there.
What else we have? I mentioned new
mobile app.
And again, we will have separate session
about new mobile app. I just want to
show you basic things. So, this is
available right now in a preview. So,
only for testing, but this is this is
available. You can find our our
documentation links from where you can
download the new mobile app.
And when you download it, works on both
iPhone and Android, you can use you can
scan your receipts. When you want to
scan your receipt, you can see in this
example, the system will automatically
crop your receipt, so regardless what is
in the background, you can have
whatever, you can just scan, and system
automatically crop, and only receipt
will be uploaded, not the background.
So, this is good example. and once when
this is upload the system will continue
to process. What is good, this app works
in offline mode as well. So,
uh by offline I mean you can scan all
your receipts and system will not
process when you are in offline, but
once when you have an internet, system
will automatically continue to process
and you don't need to look back.
And now, as I said for the end, we have
two compliance features.
Now, you can claim VAT in expense
report.
And um
how it works, this is not fully
automated as you can you could see for
example in a purchase of sales invoices
and this is
uh with a reason.
Because in general with expenses, um
claiming VAT is a little bit more
complex. In some countries, this is
based on the
uh on specific um authorities' rules,
you cannot do it at all.
So,
you cannot claim through uh expense
report. You must post this as a regular
invoice. In some countries, you are
allowed, but you must have specific
invoice. You cannot claim everything.
So, there are so many different rules
and we try to help so we can automate a
lot of things, but on the end, some of
accountants must review and confirm that
this is uh what they wanted or
eventually to make some corrections
based on the local rules.
So, it works only if you allow uh VAT
reclaim uh in a expense agent setup. If
you do not enable, system will not look
into your VAT specification at all.
But if you enable, system will
automatically collect all your uh VAT
details.
By VAT details, again, system will use
only for your country. So, if this is uh
receipt abroad, system will not use a
VAT because you cannot claim VAT from
another country. So, only from your
country. So, system will automatically
identify VAT from your receipt and
prepare VAT specification for each of
expenses.
And once when you have created expense
report, you will have this VAT
specification for each of lines. So,
this is not one VAT per document because
you can have multiple VAT specification
per line. Why a specification per line?
Now, imagine you have hotel bill and you
have different VAT rates for example,
for breakfast and for room. So, this is
not only one VAT rate per line, it can
be multiple VAT rates per line. So, this
is the reason why we have VAT
specification per line. The system will
automatically and mark all of them so
you need to process.
To make it, as I said, you need to
enable in the agent expense agent setup.
And then
you can
make a setup on expense categories and
expense subcategories. So, it can work
separately. If you have only one or a
category, it will be perfect. So, no no
complication, but you have, for example,
as I said in a hotel example, you can
have multiple VAT rates. So, you can go
to
subcategories. So, VAT will be different
based on the different records in
itemization.
And um
when you start working, you will get
specification, as you can see
on the screen, expense VAT
specification. And then, when you start
with expense report, system will
automatically collect all your expenses
into expense report and you will have
expense report
uh you will have VAT specification per
expense report line. So, this is what
you will get. You will have statistics
on expense report so you can see all
VAT records together for whole expense
report, of course. And when you post,
you will get what you already have set
up because system will use regularly
VAT business and product posting group.
So, you will have your GL entries and
you will have your VAT entries as well.
And the last topic in this overview is
withholding tax for employees with
expense report.
Why we have it? Uh, I will just explain
overview because we will have again
separate session about this topic.
Uh, we enable withholding tax for
vendors in a previous way, but now we
extend it to employees, because in some
situations, if you are paid for some
allowance or
uh, any expense above some limit in some
countries, you are supposed to pay tax.
So, you cannot take 5 million dollars
for per diem, for example, without
taxation. So, you need to pay tax. Now,
with this new model, you are
we are already to make different types
of uh, configuration. You can set up a
gross per net, uh, simple compound
model. So, I will not go into all these
details. So, you have a regular
withholding tax uh, posting setup. So,
you can set up everything there, and
then you can assign withholding uh,
business posting group to your
employees, and uh, you can assign
uh, the
uh, withholding product posting group to
your expense category again. So, system
will use both of them when you post
expense report, you will get withholding
taxes uh,
entries if you are above threshold you
configured. So, this is more or less
what we have as an overview.
Now, I'm asking you to watch other
sessions in this expense agent playlist,
because we have much more sessions going
much more into details to make some deep
dive in some specific situations.
So, thank you for watching this video.
>> [music]